Whoever saves one life, saves the world entire.
Schindler's List is a drama, history, war film directed by Steven Spielberg.
The true story of how businessman Oskar Schindler saved over a thousand Jewish lives from
the Nazis while they worked as slaves in his factory during World War II.
Oskar Schindler, played by Liam Neeson.
Itzhak Stern, played by Ben Kingsley.
Amon Goeth, played by Ralph Fiennes.
Emilie Schindler, played by Caroline Goodall.
Poldek Pfefferberg, played by Jonathan Sagall.
Helen Hirsch, played by Embeth Davidtz.
Schindler's List is a 1993 American epic historical drama film directed and
produced by Steven Spielberg and written by Steven Zaillian.
It is based on the historical novel Schindler's Ark (1982) by Thomas Keneally.
The film follows Oskar Schindler, a German industrialist who saved more than a thousand mostly
Polish–Jewish refugees from the Holocaust by employing them in his factories during World War II.
It stars Liam Neeson as Schindler, Ralph Fiennes as SS officer Amon Göth, and
Ben Kingsley as Schindler's Jewish accountant Itzhak Stern.
Ideas for a film about the Schindlerjuden (Schindler
Jews) were proposed as early as 1963.
Poldek Pfefferberg, one of the Schindlerjuden, made it his
life's mission to tell Schindler's story.
Spielberg became interested when executive Sidney Sheinberg
sent him a book review of Schindler's Ark.
Universal Pictures bought the rights to the novel, but Spielberg, unsure if he was ready to make a film about the
Holocaust, tried to pass the project to several directors before deciding to direct it himself.
Principal photography took place in Kraków, Poland, over 72 days in 1993.
Spielberg shot in black and white and approached the film as a documentary.
Cinematographer Janusz Kamiński wanted to create a sense of timelessness.
John Williams composed the score, and violinist
Itzhak Perlman performed the main theme.
Schindler's List premiered on November 30, 1993, in Washington, D.C., and
was released on December 15, 1993, in the United States.
The film received widespread critical acclaim, particularly for the performances of Neeson and Fiennes,
Williams' musical score, Kaminski's cinematography, Zaillian's screenplay, and Spielberg's direction.
It was a box office success, earning $322.2 million
worldwide on a $22 million budget.
Schindler's List earned multiple accolades, including seven Academy Awards
(including Best Picture), seven BAFTAs and three Golden Globes.
It is often listed as one of the greatest films ever made.
The film was deemed "culturally, historically or aesthetically significant" by the
Library of Congress in 2004 and selected for preservation in the U.S.
National Film Registry.
In 2007, the American Film Institute ranked Schindler's List 8th
on its list of the 100 greatest American films.
The film explores themes of factory, hero, nazi,
concentration camp, ss (nazi schutzstaffel).
The tone is emotional.